Guide to the Ethical Culture Fieldston School Records 1879-2017 MS 3042
New-York Historical Society
Ethical Culture Fieldston School records
1879-2017
New-York Historical Society
Ethical Culture Fieldston School
MS 3042
684
470.14 Linear feet in 396 containers and 25 flat files, of various sizes.
The records are the archives of the Ethical Cultural Fieldston School, documenting its history from the late 1870s to the early twenty-first century. The records relate to school governance and administration, academics, student life, extracurricular activities, special programming such as camps, parent-teacher association, buildings and facilities, publications, alumni relations, and more.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in eighteen record groups:
Record Group 1. Governance, administration, and 3-School affairs
Record Group 2. Early and defunct schools
Record Group 3. Fieldston School
Record Group 4. Midtown Ethical Culture School
Record Group 5. Fieldston Lower
Record Group 6. Camps and programs
Record Group 7. Parent and Teacher Association
Record Group 8. Alumni and alumni-relations
Record Group 9. Development and communications
Record Group 10. Buildings and grounds
Record Group 11. Print matter
Record Group 12. History of the Ethical Culture Schools
Record Group 13. Ethics Department and the Society for Ethical Culture
Record Group 14. Photographs
Record Group 15. Audiovisual (Restricted. See note at series level)
Record Group 16. Artifacts
Record Group 17. Digital formats (Restricted. See note at series level)
Record group 18. Student records (Restricted. See note at series level)
Administrative History Note
The Ethical Culture Fieldston School is a private independent K-12 school with locations in Manhattan and the Bronx. The school has its origins in the Free Kindergarten, founded in Manhattan by Felix Adler in 1878. Soon after, the school expanded its grade levels and became the Workingman's School in an effort to provide education to the city's underprivileged children. In the 1890s, the school changed its name again to the Ethical Culture School (in reflection of its relationship to the Society for Ethical Culture, also founded by Adler) and began charging tuition.
In 1904, the school moved to a newly constructed building at 33 Central Park West, adjacent to the Society for Ethical Culture. This building housed all grade levels until the opening of a high school at the Fieldston campus in the Riverdale neighborhood of the Bronx in 1928. A second lower school also opened in Fieldston in 1932. In 2007, a new middle school was opened on the Riverdale campus.
For some early years of the school, classes were also conducted at a secondary location called the Branch School. An elementary education department called the Normal School or the Teacher Training Department operated from the 1890s to 1939. At various points in its history, the school has offered several summer and extracurricular programs, including a summer camp in Cooperstown, New York.
The schools have been guided by a Board of Governors, later renamed the Board of Trustees, as well as an overarching administrative department. For much of the twentieth century, this department was called the 3-School Administration, in reference to the Ethical Culture School, Fieldston Lower and Fieldston Upper. Administratively, the school was led by a rector from 1878 to 1942, as well as an educational director (later renamed head of school) from 1928 onward. Individual schools have each been led by a principal.
Founder Felix Adler served as rector from 1878-1933. He was succeeded by John L. Elliott, founder of the Hudson Guild, who served from 1933-1942. For many years, prominent members of the Society for Ethical Culture could be found acting as chairman of the Board of Governors or the educational director. Financial and administrative ties to the Society for Ethical Culture were formally dissolved in the 1990s.
Long-serving administrators include Educational Directors V.T. Thayer (1928-1948), Victoria Wagner (1954-1968), and Howard Radest (1979-1991); and Fieldston Upper Principal Luther Tate (1941-1966), the namesake of Tate Library.
Scope and Contents
The Ethical Culture Fieldston School records provide information on the administrative and academic affairs of the school from the 1880s into the twenty-first century. Themes seen throughout include progressive education, independent school administration, curriculum creation, fundraising, and budgeting. The role of ethics, arts, or sports programs in the curriculum, and the school's response to greater societal issues such as wars, racism, poverty, and environmental concerns, are often addressed.
Pre-1940 materials in the collection strongly reflect the school's early interest in "manual training" through graphic arts, mechanics, and practical skills curriculum. Later records tend to reflect the school's interest in social progressivism and move toward a college preparatory focus. In addition, the collection contains materials related to extracurricular and summer programs in several record groups, but particularly in "RG 6: Camps and Programs." In addition, "RG 2: Early and Defunct Schools" contains records of the Normal Teacher Training Department.
Themes also seen throughout the collection include: changes in standardization of education and college admissions process (see especially the records of the Eight Year Study in "RG 3: Fieldston School"), the challenges of serving underprivileged communities in an elite institution, and the rise of student activism and a changing adolescent culture beginning in the late 1960s. This last is documented in particular through the protests of the Black and Latino Students Club in 1970, which are discussed in several record groups.
Materials relating to constituent management, particularly parental involvement in school and the maintenance of alumni relations, can be found in several record groups, but especially in "RG 8: Alumni and Alumni Relations" and in "RG 9: Development and Communications."
Information about physical locations at 33 Central Park West and the Fieldston campus in the Bronx can be found in "RG 10: Buildings and Grounds," as well as in "RG 14: Photographs" and in the Board of Governors and administration records in "RG 1: Governance, Administration, and 3-School Affairs." This includes images, architectural plans, and discussion of maintenance, budgets, and space usage.
While the philosophical influence of the Society for Ethical Culture can be seen in administrative and curriculum materials throughout the collection, directly related items consist of Society-produced ephemera, discussion of shared spaces at the Central Park West location, and the financial and legal documents detailing the dissolution of financial ties formalized in 1996.
Correspondence, meeting materials, and administrative documents make up much of the collection, along with ephemera, curriculum materials, student work, and a significant number of photographs. Most materials were created by the 3-School administration, or by the administration of individual schools, with some materials created or collected by teachers or students. Beginning in the 1980s, the Alumni Affairs department played a large role in growing the archival collection by saving contemporary items and collecting donations of older items from alumni and their descendants.
A very small amount of records relate to photographer Lewis Hine, who taught photography at the Ethical Culture School in the early twentieth century. "RG 14: Photographs" contains copy photographs and copy negatives, along with two photographs marked as possible Hine images. Other mentions of Hine in the collection are later correspondence related to archival inquiries or publicity efforts. Also, while there are very few items directly related to the school's many notable alumni, possible sources of information on individual students include class lists and student rosters from 1891 onward, as well as Fieldston yearbooks and the Fieldston News student newspaper after 1928 found in "RG 11: Print Matter."
More detailed information can be found in the description for each individual Record Group and Series. Researchers should be aware that Columbia University Rare Book & Manuscript Library holds the papers of founder Felix Adler (The Felix Adler papers, 1830-1933), as well as records relating to Adler's successor as rector, John Lovejoy Elliott, in the Hudson Guild records, 1896-1990s.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of The Ethical Culture Fieldston School, August 2017. Ethical Culture Fieldston also generously provided the funding to support the processing of the archive.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers. Access to certain materials are restricted; these restrictions are noted at the series level.
Materials are stored offsite and advance notice is required for use. Please contact manuscripts@nyhistory.org at least two business days prior to your research visit to coordinate access.
Alumni and alumnae.; Education -- New York (State) -- New York.; Moral education.; Parents' and teachers' associations -- New York (State) -- New York.; Private schools -- New York (State) -- New York.; School administrators -- New York (State) -- New York.; School management and organization -- New York (State) -- New York.; School sports.; School supervision -- New York (State) -- New York.; Student publications -- New York (State) -- New York.; Students -- New York (State) -- New York.; Teachers colleges -- New York (State) -- New York.; Ethical Culture Fieldston School -- Archives.; Society for Ethical Culture; Adler, Felix, 1851-1933; Elliott, John Lovejoy, 1868-1942
- Record Group 1. Governance, administration, and 3-School affairs (1888-2016; 64.42 linear feet), 216900; 64.42 Linear feet
  Scope and Contents Note
  This record group primarily contains materials related to the governance and administration of the Ethical Culture Fieldston Schools. Nearly all records were created in the twentieth century, with the bulk created between 1930 and 1999. Most records were created by the Board of Governors or the ECFS administration, and cover topics including finances, staffing, fund-raising, physical plant, technology, social issues, educational theory, and long-term planning. Files for head of school positions (rectors, superintendents, and 3-School directors) are also included. Common types of materials found throughout include meeting minutes, correspondence, and reports.
  In addition, this record group contains information on faculty and staff, as well as student registration data, from all three schools. Principals' annual reports to the Board of Governors also provide information on individual schools. Other materials related to specific schools can be found in their respective record groups.
  Generally, development and public relations materials can be found in Record Group 9: Development and Marketing, but some materials in RG1 relate to these efforts. (For example, discussion of publicity in Board of Governors minutes.)
  Arrangement Note
  This record group is arranged in six series:
  Series I. Board of Governors
  Series II. Rectors and Superintendent
  Series III. 3-School administration
  Series IV. Office of the 3-School Director
  Series V. Admissions and registration
  Series VI. Faculty and staff
  - Series I. Board of Governors, 1903-2004; 216901; 14.5 Linear feet
    This series is made up of materials related to the Board of Governors (renamed the Board of Trustees in 1996). Materials include items created by members of Board, as well as items created for use by the Board, such as administrative reports. Records were created between 1903 and 2001, with the bulk of materials in the series created sometime between 1930 and 1990. The majority of items are routine documents, such as meeting minutes and annual status reports, with some correspondence and notes from various chairmen of the Board, as well as long-time Board member Nanette Rothschild.
    This series is arranged in six subseries:
    Subseries I.A. Board of Governors: Incorporation, by-laws, minutes, and finances
    Subseries I.B. Committees
    Subseries I.C. Reports from the Principals, Directors, and other administrative officers
    Subseries I.D. Chairman of the Board - Marie S. Neuberger Papers
    Subseries I.E. Chairman of the Board - Joseph Jablonower papers
    Subseries I.F. Nanette F. Rothschild Papers
    - Subseries I.A Board of Governors: Incorporation, by-laws, minutes, and finances, 1903-2004; 217026
      This subseries primarily contains minutes for meetings of the Board of Governors (later the Board of Trustees), accompanied by meeting agendas, reports from committees, supplementary meeting materials, and related correspondence. Frequent topics of discussion include finances, enrollment, scholarships, collection of tuition, fundraising, faculty and staff, and buildings and grounds.
      While most minutes are concerned with strategy or administrative matters, discussions involving the ethics programs and educational philosophy are included. Issues of racial or economic diversity are also discussed, such as in a 1908 declaration of "non-discrimination by color."
      Earlier Board records are more likely to concern individual families or faculty members, or quotidian school business, with discussions moving towards higher level issues throughout the twentieth century. Many files include Executive Committee information (earliest records use the name House Committee). Records from 1981 through 1987 consist of complete mailings sent to Board members. Minutes prior to 1945 are largely facsimiles, not original documents.
      Board minutes can also be found in the papers of Chairmen of the Board subseries, or in the Office of the Director series.
      Other than minutes, this subseries contains financial documents related to the Board, and some other miscellaneous Board materials.
      This subseries is arranged by type of document, and then chronologically within each group.
      - School incorporation, accreditation, and by-laws (3 folders), 1903-1984; 222433 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1-3)
        Facsimiles of correspondence regarding incorporation of the school. Facsimile of Certificate of Incorporation of the Society for Ethical Culture with New York State, 1925. Copies of by-laws (printed booklets and photocopies).
      - Minutes and correspondence of the Board of Governors (27 folders), 1903-1964; 222476 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4-30)
      - Minutes and correspondence of the Board of Governors (26 folders), 1965-1987; 222477 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 1-26)
      - Minutes and correspondence of the Board of Governors (20 folders), 1988-2004; 222481 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 1-20)
      - Financial documents (4 folders), 1906-1993; 222485 (Offsite-box 46, Folder 1-4)
        Includes intermittent correspondence, 1950s budget analysis, and 1990-1991 "Interschool Comparative Study" with financial aid comparisons between other New York schools.
      - Financial statements (14 folders), 1971-2002; 222490 (Offsite-box 46, Folder 5-18)
        Reports from external accountants for the Ethical Culture Schools.
      - Lists of Board of Governors members (7 folders), 1939-2000; 222534 (Offsite-box 47, Folder 1-7)
        Lists of members of the Board of Governors, as well as some lists of guests at meetings and committee assignments.
      - Miscellaneous documents (12 folders), 1909-2004, undated; 222535 (Offsite-box 47, Folder 8-19)
        Miscellaneous statements and correspondence. Examples of specific items include: correspondence of Chairman Frank Karelson, workshop and retreat materials, correspondence of the chair of the Sinaiko Property Committee (1969-1976), Law Committee materials (1974-1979), and a 1909 booklet printed in memorium of Chairman Alfred R. Wolff.
    - Subseries I.B Committees, 1936-1999; 217027
      Types of materials in this subseries include minutes, reports, notes, and a small amount of correspondence, for Board-level committees. Some minutes and reports are found within the overall Board of Governors meeting minutes.
      Executive Committee minutes cover similar high-level issues as the overall Board of Governors minutes. External events and issues are often reflected in school agenda items, such as in a 1968 mention of "Anti-War Activities" on campus.
      This subseries is divided into records of the Executive Committee and records of other committees, then arranged chronologically within each group.
      - Executive Committee minutes and correspondence (7 folders), 1936-1941, 1947-1956; 222494 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 21-27)
      - Executive Committee minutes and correspondence (31 folders), 1956-1996; 222525 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 1-31)
        Files include the Ethical Culture Schools – District 9 Cooperative Program Annual Report, 1976-1977.
      - Committee minutes and reports (8 folders), 1949-1999; 222495 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 32-39)
        File include minutes, reports, and notes from the following committees: Director's Search Committee (1970-1979), Education Committee (1983-1990), Enrollment Committee (1949), Committee on Finance and Budget (1954), Finance Committee (1999), Committee on Organization of School (1932).
      - Committee minutes and reports (8 folders), 1945-1990; 222526 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 1-8)
        File include minutes, reports, and notes from the following committees: Planning Committees (1982-1990), Principal's Search Committee (1986), Rectorship Committee (1945), Salary Review Committee (1964), and Structure Committees (1973-1978). Some minutes and reports are interfiled with overall Board of Governors meeting minutes.
    - Subseries I.C Reports from the Principals, Directors, and other administrative officers, 1934-2000; 217028
      This subseries consists of reports on administrative and educational issues during the school year at Ethical Cultures Schools. Types of reports vary each year, but nearly all files contain an overall report from the 3-Schools director, along with individual school reports from principals, and sometimes reports from the assistant director, registrar or admissions departments. Many of the reports from the 1930s also have sections written by academic department heads, or reports from the Branch School. Towards the end of the twentieth century, all files begin to include reports from the alumni and development office and the director of admissions and financial aid.
      Generally, each principal's report provides a summary of the year's events, departmental issues, new hires, and achievements in teacher and student performance. Reports from directors and assistant directors attempt to confront larger school issues, focusing on budgets, development, faculty and student morale, and facilities. Many reports provide thoughts on ethics issues, parental involvement in the schools, trends in educational theory, technology, and the school's response to larger events and issues, including World War II, the Civil Rights Movement, and the Vietnam War. Occasionally, the administration also makes recommendations or poses questions to the Board.
      Earliest reports consist of a lengthy qualitative analysis and personal reflection, with a very small amount of quantitative information (often a college matriculation list). Through the twentieth century, written sections shorten and the amount of quantitative information and data tables increases. 1945 onward, Ethical Culture Schools reports include registration reports with enrollment data. Beginning in the late 1950s, reports of the assistant to the director include a good deal of financial and fundraising information. From the 1960s onward, each year contains a separate report from the registrar's office. Special or ad hoc reports become more common in the second half of the 20th century.
      Some files include an accompanying letter from the director, and the 1973 report also includes a letter from the Board in response to the director's report.
      This subseries is divided into annual and special reports, then arranged chronologically within each group.
      - Annual reports to the Board of Governors (15 folders), 1934-1948; 222531 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 9-23)
        The 1939-1940 Fieldston School report appendix includes sample forms, such as report cards.
      - Annual reports to the Board of Governors (15 folders), 1949-1963; 222982 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 1-15)
        1960 Fieldston School report includes Report of the Committee on Academic Honesty.
      - Annual reports to the Board of Governors, 1963-1977; 222983 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 1-16)
        1963-1964 director's report is titled, "After Civil Rights – What?" Civil rights are also discussed in the report of Fieldston Principal Luther Tate that year. During the late 1960s and early 1970s, reports contain considerable discussion of social justice issues and shifts in student behavior and family situations (for example, families with two parents working outside of the home).
      - Annual reports to the Board of Governors (21 folders), 1977-2000; 222984 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 1-21)
        Report types become more varied during this time period. Examples include: 1978 reports from the director of the Fieldston day camp and from the coordinator of educational philosophy, a 1979 report on an "Intercultural Exchange Program" between Fieldston and P.S. 98, and a 1996 report titled "Technology at ECF – A Status Report." Long-range planning reports, Ethical Fieldston Fund information, and Parent & Teacher's Association reports are also seen. Computers and new technology are frequently discussed.
      - Special reports to the Board of Governors (2 folders), 1963-1996, undated; 222532 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 22-23)
        One-off reports and memos to the board. Includes reports and memos from Luther Tate, Howard Radest, and Frank Karelson.
    - Subseries I.D Chairman of the Board - Marie S. Neuberger Papers, 1934-1989; 217032
      Materials of Marie S. Neuberger, including those created during her tenure as chairman of the Board from 1955-1964.
      In this subseries, correspondence and Board of Governors records are arranged chronologically, while subject files are arranged alphabetically.
      - Correspondence (5 folders), 1953-1964; 222537 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 1-5)
        Incoming correspondence and copies of outgoing correspondence with parents, administrators and other Board members. Topics include donations, admissions, publicity, and committee work.
      - Board of Governors (5 folders), 1957-1989; 222538 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 6-10)
        Minutes, Advisory Council correspondence, reports to the Board and other related documents.
      - Board of Governors - committees (15 folders), 1953-1969; 222540 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 11-25)
        Minutes and correspondence for the Enrollment Committee, Executive Committee, Planning Committee, and the Tate Library Committee. Fund-raising and planning documents for the Tate Library Committee.
      - Subject files A-F (4 folders), 1948-1980; 222541 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 26-29)
        Files involving the Advisory Council (1955-1964), the search for Director Wagner's replacement (1967-1979), the Ethics Program (1976-1980), and faculty issues (1948-1977).
      - Subject files F-T (9 folders), 1934-1982; 222542 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 1-9)
        Files involving finances (1934-1982), fundraising (1954-1964), real estate (1964-1967), school policies (1960-1980), and administrative organization (1967-1981).
    - Subseries I.E Chairman of the Board - Joseph Jablonower papers, 1936-1952; 222536
      Materials of Joseph Jablonower, including those created during his tenure as Chairman of the Board from 1945-1951.